[Applause] visit the Dhammapada verse which I think
visit the Dhammapada verse which I think
deals with what one of the
and boy number 11 and 12
those who mistake the uh nacelle to be
essential and is essential to be an
essentialist dwelling in wrong purposeful quartz
dwelling in wrong purposeful quartz
never arrived at the essential those who
know the essential to be essential and
an essential to be onion central
dwelling in right purposeful thoughts
arrive at the essentials somewhat
sometime knowing what you want knowing
the right being your purpose what you
got you really want take freedom from
sorrow so it's the it's the most
fundamental context of the holy life
it's the freedom from suffering that's
as the Buddha said himself like the sea
has only one taste of salt sort of
damage only one taste of freedom from
suffering and again you can take that in
a sort of general descriptive manner yes
freedom from suffering but you can also
take that in a manner of quite a quadric
used form of of correct contemplation
like develop the theme of being free
from suffering contemplated maintain it
sort of maintain it in your mind have it
endure in your mind don't forget about
it
don't lose perspective on it because if
you had faith to begin with in the
Buddhist teachings that offer you
possible way out of suffering that means
you you you will also if you don't lose
perspective had have faith in all the
other instructions he gave the reasons
for celibacy the reasons for virtue it
won't be as hard because you have faith
and you will see it pertaining to the
goal because you have that perspective
that's right
faith is also could also be enough for
somebody to make effort so you don't
necessarily need
have it all figured out but if you have
faith in the right instruction and you
do it rightly but that doesn't mean you
can sacrifice your perspective on it so
the faith can help you if the
perspective hasn't been compromised if
the purpose hasn't been obscured why are
you doing this why you're a monk or why
are you practicing Dhamma to be free
from suffering so you always keep that
at the back of your mind that purpose
and that's how you can get to get to
differentiate more and more things that
are then compatible with it and things
that are not incompatible and above all
you could that's how you can also become
aware of your own responsibility for it
like your own habits of craving that
revolve around random things you'll see
wait a minute why am I doing this
because I have perspective this is
what's important to me to be free from
suffering yet Here I am like feverishly
engaged with this strategy what's the
purpose of that and as I can't seem to
be able to stop why not cuz you lost
perspective you regain perspective
stopping restraining becomes effortless
or certainly requires less effort
so gaining perspective makes things a
lot yes meant gaining perspective and
maintaining perspective makes things
more easy because why because the
purpose is not obscured or it's a
degenerated you know like even as we
mentioned that the other day like even
in the lay world of people not
necessarily interested in facts of
Buddhism the motivational speakers and
so on talked about finding the purpose
for your life because without it you're
gonna be depressed or you'll be just
wandering aimlessly or just scratching
essential attain they are nothing but
finding a purpose gives you that meaning
which then makes actions much more
easier to do Duty easier to do
restrained enduring things much easier
to do cuz you have a greater purpose so
you can make a practice out of
maintaining through contemplation
maintaining in the back of your mind not
actively I want to be free from
suffering I want to be free from
suffering just remind yourself and then
let it endure without forgetting about
it not actually thinking about
but not forgetting about it either
that's the practice of mindfulness in
the nutshell what is the point yeah sure
yeah you can like reevaluate not in a
sense of reevaluate or what am i what am
i doing but even that if you feel
necessary sometimes but we want to be
really just maintaining the direction of
your practice that you already know
that's the whole point so that's a they
come and that practice you're
questioning we discussed before you
question yourself as a form of
contemplation not to necessarily find
the right answer but more like to induce
the right attitude they will then bring
that perspective back or clarified or
introduce new perspectives you won't be
given the right answer because it's not
it's not like a quiz question it's more
like discerning the things that are
already there but you need to see them
with the right type of eyes you need to
recognize them you need to recognize the
the nature of impermanence the nature of
non ownership and so on that's all there
already but not recognizing it means
it's not there for you because it's not
being seen so if you have a question
like it doesn't even need to be anything
specific or technical it just as we said
you remind yourself or you ask yourself
why am i practicing what's the purpose
I've been doing this Buddhist practice
for a number of years
what what's the purpose of that doesn't
matter how far you got into that
practice how much you know you can
always ask yourself that question and if
you do it rightly you will just
reestablish the perspective or just
remind yourself that that perspective is
still there either way it's going to
result in mindfulness so if you if your
question is what am i practicing whether
you're a beginner or not a beginner you
ask us of that and don't jump at the
answer don't rush it because of this you
know just what's the point of this and you'll
just what's the point of this and you'll
see that the answer is already there
otherwise you wouldn't have been doing
it for all these years the point is as
the point always was freedom from
suffering so if you don't feel perhaps
that you are free from suffering enough
then you can press the questions further
again not just so that you can find the
right answer they will please you but
more like that through that attitude of
questioning you will start to look in
the direction different from the
ready-made answer they would come your
way the question that will inevitably
then have to result in in greater
perspective eventually it might be more
ambiguous perspective and that's where
people fear to question their own
beliefs their own efforts because by
putting it in question means you're
already questioning well you're already
implying that it could have also been
invalid so I must not question it then
that's how we'll not think about a
possibility of me being wrong for
example but if you always question
yourself that becomes your perspective
and that's how actually you cannot be
affected if a thing does change because
you haven't been emotionally invested in
it and certainly haven't invested like a
form of well invested by ignorant like
oh I ignore this I'm not going to
question this because simply putting it
in question that ambiguity causes me
anxiety and that's why we're not
question it but that's completely the
opposite attitude of the attitude you
should have if you want to be free from
suffering
to give you an example well the example
would be why am i practicing because I
want to be free from suffering am i free
from suffering so if the answer to that
is no you know the owns you know the
answer and we fundamentally ultimately
beyond suffering if the answer is yes
great you know you already know what
you're doing but the answer is no or I'm
not sure means okay so all these efforts
have been making yet I'm still not free
from suffering perhaps I was wrong not
like that the Buddha's teaching was
wrong but perhaps I haven't been doing
it rightly and again you might now
because you know all the investment of
your effort and emotionally-charged
practice that you've been doing for a
number of years it will make that person
uncomfortable if you start questioning
you like that it's going to make you
uncomfortable what if these 20 years of my meditation
what if these 20 years of my meditation
methods and techniques and I'm not free
from suffering what if what if I've been
doing is wrong
could I start again so the sooner you
started questioning the less less of an
emotional investment it will become if
you've been doing it wrong in other
words if you come back on questioning
from the start or if you start
questioning as soon as you become aware
of that you should questioning it's it's
still a good thing because it will
prevent you from proliferating further
if it were the wrong way and again if it
were not the wrong way you would have
been free from suffering by now
so then you really well you it but not
level but whatever here I might have
been wrong but again what is my purpose
to never be wrong or to be free from
suffering to be free from suffering so
doesn't matter even if 400 years have
been wrong now I can be right then now I
know that everything I've done is wrong
which means it's less likely that I'll
repeat the same mistakes cuz I admitted
it to myself but if you never questioned
it never admit it
you will then blindly just go and keep
repeating the same thing that you deep
down inside no it doesn't work because
it hasn't free from suffering after all
this time and even as a child said
himself if you don't become a soda bun
in the first 5 years of practice you're
not doing it right if you don't get the
right view within the first five years
of becoming a monk committed to you're
not doing it right and that's quite
accurate you're not doing it right and
you should really like reevaluate
quickly because the more you invest in
the wrong way through the harder it will
be to undo it because more concede gets
involved more Center self and also like
more of that like oh I'm not gonna look
at this because it's becoming the more
you ignore it the more unpleasant it
will be to face it later on so a simple
question am i free from suffering if you
know you're not free from suffering you
can as you said you can ask yourself why
am i suffering but again don't well I'm
suffering because and then give some
stock phrase answer no ask yourself why
am i suffering without and then like
restrained the answer don't answer it
just let the question endure just remind
yourself why am i suffering and let it
endure because it will prevent by
allowing the question to endure not
jumping jumping it an answer it will it
forces you to adopt a perspective by
refraining from jumping into the answer
and that perspective it's going to be
ambiguous it's going to be unpleasant
but it's still a perspective and it's
still better than just providing a quick
answer that's going to turn a blind eye
to any greater perspective so similar to
judgmental it is but not judgmental for
the sake of non judgment because I'm
non-judgmental well that can become your
judgment because you started doing it
mechanically if you ask yourself am i
judgemental and don't answer it
certainly don't answer it right away
that's going to force you to endure with
that ambiguity am i yes or am I not
because he's saying am i judgemental
saying yes means you're judgmental
saying no means you're judgmental MA
judgmental no I'm not judgmental you
just made the judgment that you are not
judgmental that's how I mean why am i
suffering but don't answer it in that
sense but simply look at the question of
why am i suffering
don't try to collect information about
it but why am i suffering so when you
ask yourself why am i suffering
what are you directing the question at
will you directing it at the actual
suffering or there the possibility to
suffer order the fact that you're not
free from suffering okay so I'm not free
from suffering otherwise I wouldn't even
ask myself why am i suffering so that's
already first recognition that comes
simply from that right perspective that
comes out of the right question so why
am i suffering then what I don't know
certainly I cannot define it not at this
stage so why am i suffering then oh i
suffer because suffering is present what
I suffer is suffering doesn't manifest
No
so I suffer when suffering is manifest
yes do I have a say in that for example
we can ask that do I have a say in
suffering being manifest well I might
have seen things I do but do I have say
in the unpleasant feeling being
manifested in Enderlin no because if I
had to say it would disappear whenever I
tell it then he wouldn't even appear
because I don't want it to appear so I
don't have I am liable to these feelings
in the same sense the weather changes
and I can't even conceive stopping or
preventing it so is then that
disagreeable feeling is that my
suffering is the disagreeable mood that comes my
is the disagreeable mood that comes my
way that have no say in it
and I can't do anything about it is that
why be he's dead because of why like
he's there the reason why I suffer and
again yes no don't tell me is that these
are my disagreeable feelings
is that what my suffering is let that in
do I didn't do for days if nothing
presents itself by having perspective on
such questioning that pertains to these
universal natures
so to speak you are looking at that
direction which means there is a chance
of you discerning things rightly but if
you just give a stock answer or the
answer you think it should be you stop
looking because you provided the answer
and even though yet this house is
Beverly right fine but let me keep
looking that's right women by self
interrogation and questioning or then
you go and visit people who think
they're wiser than you you know they're
wiser and let them interview question
cuz it will bring all these
possibilities of developing these
perspectives through self questioning
that undoes the ignorance and does the
last in a version so why am i suffering
why am I not free from suffering
you don't have to answer just become
fully aware of it not for some sort of
mystical revelation simply you want that
perspective or they're questioning
existential questioning to endure
because by enduring you become more
familiar with it so why am I not free
from suffering okay let's get some
guideline guidelines in regard to that
what did the Buddha say why are you not
free from suffering because there is
craving you crave oh so I'm not free
from suffering because I still crave
craving regard to what but craving is on
the level of your doing not on the level
of some placement yeah did you you can
say where is the feeling in a way
because you haven't created it
you're liable to it so what is the
correct what is the craving yeah any you
don't have to overthink how should I ask
this question the point is questioning
the subject questioning the phenomena
will at least start inducing some
perspective on it so where is where is
the craving okay where is the craving
well craving is in regard to the feeling
that's what Buddha said okay but now I
need to understand that I can't just
give the answer that I read in the
sutras so what is the feeling that as we
just discussed feeling is that that I'm
liable to feeling is that that I have no
sane so they're these phenomena one at a
time Pleasant unpleasant or neutral they
come my way and I'm not saying that I've
absolutely no saying that I cannot
prevent them from arising I cannot tell
them to stay longer or to disappear
quicker I'm fully liable to so I cannot
I'm fully liable to so I cannot
influence that but what is it that I can
influence on the basis of those those
phenomena you're feeling it's your own
attitude towards feel your own fear not
towards the world that caused these
feelings it's over the feelings that you
feel right there and then whatever
present feeling is it's your attitude
alert to it that's what craving is so if
you stop resisting the feeling if
stop indulging the feeling if you stop
ignoring the feeling you will not be
able to crave for the feeling if you're
not able to crave for the feeling how
can you suffer on account the feeling
hence craving leads to suffering absence
of craving leads to freedom from
suffering I'm giving answers now sure it came out
I'm giving answers now sure it came out
of questioning the right things of
course so that's what I mean like you
can't just start questioning things
right without any knowledge you need to
read the sutras so you know what
questions think so if you as you ask
yourself a question about training
makes you look yeah you see craving not
not in the same sense as you can see
like oh I'm feeling Pleasant afternoon
class oh yeah there is craving right in
front of me because that will make it an
independent phenomenon in the phenomena
it's independent of your attitude but it
isn't that's why craving your assumptions are
that's why craving your assumptions are
negative phenomena in a sense you can
see that in regard to which your
attitude is being sort of exercised and
then you realize my attitude is wrong so
I'm doing the attitude undoes the
craving that's where the Buddha said the
opah donna like the in the assumption
it's not the five aggregates but there
is no assumption without the five
aggregates you can say the same for
craving craving is not in regard to the
feeling but there is no craving apart
from feeling it's the desire and lust in
regard to feeling that craving is there
its desire and lust in regard to the
five aggregates they do Padang is there
you remove these rlist
there is no basis for you karana to be
manifested or there is no basis for
craving to be manifested that's what I
mean if you give the positive answer to
what craving is you think that's what
craving is which means you're not
looking now on the level of your
attitude so that's a am i suffering yes
and we're free from suffering no what is
the cause of suffering craving okay now
I give that answer but now I need to
understand that answer you cannot serve
what is my craving well I don't know but
I know that whenever suffering is
craving is that's where the Buddha said
so if I don't suffer if I'm free from
suffering there is no craving but if I'm
not free from suffering so whenever
there is suffering
my experience craving must be there also
to the same extent
so suffering and craving are inseparable
so that's a conclusion you arrived by
not jumping on it on to the immediate
answer so ours
am i suffering and you know I'm not that
makes me look at that phenomena which
I'm talking about yeah so why am i
suffering and now you have all these
suitors you read about suffering coming
up to mind that's fun don't ignore it
but don't just yes I'm suffering because
of this that answer doesn't apply to you
so I'm suffering because of craving okay
but why am i suffering oh so now you can
provide even more accurate answer why am
i suffering
well suffering is because of craving so
why am i suffering up because I haven't
understood craving so the opposite of
the Buddha gave that is correct answer I
haven't understood which is why I'm
suffering so that would be more accurate
answer to that question that you arrived
at by not jumping at the first offer
answered by your mind why am i suffering
because of craving is present in sin
Cara's okay suffering is because of sin
Cara's in because of craving why am i
suffering or because I haven't
understood so card has no the craving
that's why I am suffering that's why I'm
liable to suffer so if you won't
understand it you start questioning that
what is craving is you said a wave is
craving or why do I crave any question
they will revolve around the phenomenon
of craving at least implies that did I
designate that direction so you don't
try to oh well see he said this that
answer pleases me that's why I'm
suffering no that also pleases me maybe
for right maybe for wrong reasons but
that's not why I suffer I suffer because
I haven't understood that answer
so that's why it takes effort to develop
the skill of contemplating things
rightly you can't just know why is this
happening to me and expect some wisdom
to come out of it although it's a
necessary step if a person doesn't start
questioning their own existence
why am i suffering they'll never look to
further for the way up because yeah
there are people who will never ask that
question to themselves and they'll never
ever make any effort with practice or
anything anything remotely to freed
himself from suffering you can also use
that as as what we spoke the other day
about the theme my ability to suffering
you can establish it on like peripheral
in your mind don't think about it I'm
suffering I might just have it there is
a background of whatever you go through
in your day-to-day life Oh suffering
might be form and again anybody can do
that you don't need great instruction
for it you just need to be well brave in
a way you need to have courage to admit
it to yourself that yes because it's the
truth it's not that you are fabricating
it when you think about it which is what
usually people will develop attitude as
a form of self kind of defense mechanism
now if I think about it that's how I
know I stopped thinking about it and
that's how I'm happy that's how I don't
suffer until you suffer by then it's too
late to do anything about it
also you must not think about suffering
because it's neurotic well where this
neurotic or not it's beside the point
the point is that it's the truth you are
liable to suffering at any given moment
in your life so if you have that
strength to admit that to yourself
gradually it becomes the theme and
that's the theme that the Buddha said
it's the necessary theme for somebody to
seek the the homeless life in practice
toward Nibbana say a young man realizes
he's prey to suffering
exactly like imagine and we spoke about
before probably but it doesn't hurt to
repeat it like many people would read
over that line or is prey to suffering
yes yes but no make a theme out of it
hande understand it how would you feel
if you were prey
if there is a nonspecific non-defined
like ubiquitous sort of presence of a
hunter but you can't see it but you know
it's hunting you you would feel like
constantly something can pounce on you
by Yuna can never see from what
direction so it's quite a profound
existential sort of anxiety and state
and the Buddha said that is the
necessary step when he recognized I am
prayed to suffering why don't I go and
do something about this so he didn't
fabricate it
he basically discerned that theme
because that theme was the right thing
because you are truly prey to suffering
and how would you feel if like you go on
throughout the day and some and people
tell you oh wait like there is an
assassin stalking you
you don't know when he's gonna hit you
where nor how but you know it will you
would be on a constant alert
involuntarily like it wouldn't be you do
you do you don't need to make the effort
you're gonna have to make the effort to
distract yourself from it from the
pressing truth and that's why it's hard
for people to practice restraint and
give up habits and lay life because
that's the dead part of that
self-defense mechanism from admitting
the most fundamental basic truth then
you are not your own self in a sense of
you are not in control of your own
existence which means you are liable to
misfortune to accidents to youa liable
to you are prey to suffering not to this
person or to that to government law you
are prey to the unpleasant feeling
arising within yourself suffering is
hunting you down
and you do dwell on that theme and
you're only gonna have one result
seeking out liberation from suffering
because that's the whole life is about
defense mechanism from that so why don't
you then make the effort you know what
if you were to make the effort and
uproot it means no other effort is
required no other maintenance not the
Scheldt nor the defense mechanism
nothing is required that's true freedom
no pressure no burden I must do this I
must do that if I don't fix this
suffering will come if I don't do that
well that'll be unpleasant
there's nothing for you to do because
there's nothing for you they can make
you suffer and again that's not it can
become mindless conceptualize just theme
yes I'm suffering I'm suffering but
that's when you lost your mindfulness
but if you remind yourself that I
shouldn't be given this answer I should
be discerning these answers on the basis
of the present situation because present
situation shows me the nature that I am
still liable to suffering which means
the theme is there the theme of
suffering and freedom from it is already
there whether you answer it or not is
secondary [Applause]
so you can walk around feeling like your
prey to suffer doesn't matter how
careful you are what well but obviously
it's gonna make you more careful but you
realize that no man of your action can
prevent you from experiencing the
unpleasant feeling if it chooses to come
so by admitting this to yourself then
you will you get to recognize that your
defense from unpleasant feeling is not
about preventing it to come your defense
from the unpleasant feeling is about
preventing yourself from resisting it
from implying that you can do something
about it
and that's how you prevent yourself from
craving and then you also realize okay
so if I want to do that I equally then
cannot be careless in regard to pleasant
feeling because pleasant feeling
unpleasant feeling it's the feeling it's
that thing I'm trying to free myself
from I can't just free myself from
unpleasant feelings and only maintain
pleasant feelings there's a cherry pick
the ones I want no feeling is the
problem because I'm liable to it by
accepting the liability to pleasant
feeling means I make myself equally
liable to the unpleasant feeling that's
right like the sense restraint becomes
self-evident
because it reveals feelings yeah well
reveals the feelings that basically just
mirrors then what your attitudes there
you realize that or when pleasant
feeling is there my attitude is full
acceptance full welcoming full delight
but it's the exercising of any attitude
towards any feeling
that's why craving is there so removing
that will mean you realize many people
until they realize will be blaming the
feeling blaming that which calls the
feeling blaming the world blaming others
blaming themselves the point is you're
liable to feeling where you want to be
or not so you recognize I can't I don't
have a saying that and I should stop
trying to change that and that reveals
then that what you can change is then
your own overly welcoming feeling or
overly resisting based on whether they
are agreeable or disagreeable or being
careless about them if they're neutral
access to you if you do you yeah that is
what suffering is yeah that access is
the suffering and that's completely on
you not on the feeling craving is not in
the feeling in as much Appa Don is not
in the aggregate you look at the
aggregates you're not gonna super done
you're only gonna see aggregate what is
that desire and lust desire I want this
desire I don't want this that's why
craving is there in regard to it like a
parasite as in a villa terror with this
cravat that's why this this question yes
be done before you can also ask yourself
again not for the sake of answer or for
the sake of establishing an enduring
perspective what am I feeling right now
fundamentally overall at the most
beautiful corners of my experience
am i okay or am I not okay because
that's what the feeling is or that's
what it stretches from see I'm okay okay
so let let it in do I'm fine if you
allow it to endure then you see that
phenomena enduring for what it is and
when he changes you see that to not like
now has changed news just like for now
I'm not okay
so now there is another sort of vessel
of your mood that's holding you up now
different Oh
so before he was okay now it's not okay
did I have the same between no I didn't
even see how it changed he just came all
so that means that whatever has come it
will have to go for the same reason that
he came on its own yeah that's true
that's already a form of like a
liberating inside but then you also
realize that nothing is worth desiring
towards nothing is worth adhering to
because yeah because it came on its own
it will have to go on its own but it
needs to be seen on that most general
contextual level Universal level now
from the level of an answer in the
theory right in front of it yeah
everything is constantly changing the
zone so if your present feeling now it's
home okay that's fine is this present
okay feeling as an agreeable feeling is
dis liable to suffering as in is it
liable to change toward into unpleasant
feeling and I will suffer on account of
it you will know that and that you know
it's that suffering is on that level of
their liability not necessarily of the
presently enduring feeling that's why
you have suffering in the pleasure as
well by not having enough of the
pleasure you crave that's why I have
suffering in the in the displeasure
because you don't want any of the
displeasure yet there is still song but
if you stop exercising their attitude
towards wanting more for not wanting any
of it and seeing it for what it is
enduring on its own you stop resisting
it you stop indulging it which means you
will stop providing the basis for
craving towards the field and that's how
free yourself from suffering
and I asked yourself how am I feeling
right now still okay still the same
feeling enduring ten minutes now and
when many changes you can carry on and
when I'm not okay
will I be bothered by it yes no okay I'm
not sure hmm well should I be sure
surely I should strive for not being
bothered by any feeling
so by questioning rightly inducing
perspective Riley you get to induce more
perspectives in in the same senses and
okay so this is what matters to me then
you get to clarify what needs to be done
as well and then you also get to
recognize important as important
essential as essential as you rather
than a father worse because you realize
okay so if I never lose the sight of
presently enduring feeling that's
independent of me can I then have any
careless attitude towards it no oh so
that's the gatekeeper that the Buddha
was talking about I don't need to be I'm
feeling okay I'm feeling that's not a
gate keeper that's you fabricating the
answer you think it is because the
feeling is already that you are already
feeling okay or not to kill whatever
you're already feeling is already there
independent of you present enduring in
your experience if you stay mindful on
that peripheral level without making it
into actual answer but without losing
sight of it you can't exercise attitude
towards like wanting it not wanting it
because you realize this is completely I
am invisible to my own feelings they
don't care about me I don't exist for
them so me trying to change them and
they just pointless just me time my own
my own self in a not and yet feeling
still remains unaffected for as long as
he wants to remain that's why other
hands would remain contemplating file a
rising and falling like enduring with
the five aggregates on their own terms
nothing for him to do so you realize oh
that's the task I should develop not
lose the sight of this general context
of the present enduring feeling and see
it will become mechanical if you forget
how you're actually feeling but if you
keep if you don't forget or if you
remind yourself you have one feeling
that is Wedman am i what is the
president in your feeling what am I
feeling plus-minus
plus-minus
okay not okay neutral what is it and
then discern that basis everything else
the context is back fully you don't need
to go to the motions of the ant-like the
answers that pop before or read the
sutras to
use them no it's right there it was
always right there and then you have you
have a gatekeeper
should I be walking slowly and try not
to lapse for a single second no that's
pointless that's like misdirected all I
need to do is not forget the present
enduring feeling is out of my control
and I will refrain from carelessly
indulging it and I will refrain from
carelessly trying to get rid of it and
now I can talk to you because that
doesn't affect my attitude towards this
feeling doesn't induce the urge to this
fear but if you say hey let's go and you
know do these things or something
unwholesome or let's go and in a big
crowd of people and it's like well I
might not necessarily do anything bad in
that situation but that situation is
certainly very incompatible with me
maintaining the perspective on the
present enduring feeling that's right
here it's too distracting so I say no to
that oh let's go to a Buddhist
conference because you know Buddhism
it's a good thing yeah but that's 3,000
people there men women no it smells
crowd what's the purpose of that what
will I learn will I learn anything I
don't know yeah so what is witty they
are rooted in in justified excitement
justify distraction because you know
it's a good cause yeah but it's a good
course universalizing conceptually for
people it's a good cause on paper but
for me it's a cause for distraction so I
don't do it cause if I distract and
that's that's why you are responsible
for your actions that you're responsible
for the basis of suffering in your own
experience because you can't
accidentally give rise to greed aversion
delusion it's always a choice that's
where you can also approach it you
choose to be careless you choose to do
actions they will then result in losing
the perspective and then do things out
of lust or anger no oh yeah yeah huge
you were fully aware of that leap that
you made
into the environment of lust or anger or
distraction you just lied to yourself at
a time but again you can't truly lie to
yourself because in order to lie you
need to cover up the truth which means
you already know what the truth is
but you choose to focus on the lie no no
no it's for the good cause it's for the
greater cause there is no greater cause
than personal suffering and freedom from
it for everyone so that's what I mean
through questioning you get to discern
the perspective then you realize oh this
is that that task that I need to do I've
been overdoing it under doing it I
didn't know what I was doing but if I
protect this mine on the level of this
peripheral presently enduring feeling
independent of me I don't need to do
anything else and whatever I do that
doesn't contradict this I'm fine
that's why you get in the suit that
sometimes instruction on the level
whatever you know it's unwholesome
unskillful incompatible abandon it
whatever you know that it's Co wholesome
skillful and compatible cultivated
cultivated as in let it remain in the
pain don't negate it don't go the
opposite way
and that's exactly how you will end up
discerning essential as essential
non-essential which is Samedi tea it's
the right view sotapanna knows skillful
is skillful unskillful is on skillful he
knows essential is essential
non-essential is non-essential because
he sees direct connection to that basis
that used to provide the suffering oh
this was fueling the basis this is
removing the basis
hence practicing for dispassion removal
of desire and lust removal of any basis
of unwholesome but again one thing is to
have these in paper is the information
which is necessary something to begin
with but another thing is to recognize
that you must be the one understanding
it on the basis of your present
experience not on a brave basis on
emotionally pleasing answer we can look
at your whole day in a way day ahead of
you you can look from that from having
established that more general
perspective all the particular actions
are you going to do throughout the day
you can you can keep this perspective at
the back of your mind
which means you will not be able to be
too long too too careless about your act
because the perspective you maintain
still maintains a degree of context
towards your particular actions even if
you don't actively think about it all
the time so if my context is freedom
from suffering I want to be free from
suffering means my context is also by
the extension a renunciation so my
context is saying no to gratuitous
desire and again you don't need to go
like now I'm going to my cutting and I'm
walking and I see notice I know my
context is a renunciation don't get
distracted by overly defining it but
certainly don't forget about it or
mystified so if your mind is established
upon the theme of renunciation anything
that's normal enunciation on the
particular level will not take your mind
away from me
that's what we meant by establishing the
mind upon that greater context like you
establish your mind upon the perceptions
of the forest so when you're in the
village no sights and sounds melted from
the village will take your mind away
because you established it you made the
effort to establish the context so
because what is the body what are the
perceptions of the forest its perception
of Solitude perception of like absence
of people a perception of non sexuality
is not centrality in the forest no sense
objects perception of hardship and those
are the things that you calculate and
you start to value and you want to
maintain at the back of your mind you
maintain that at the back of mind you
don't need to worry about what comes in
front with you you this is that's the
gatekeeper that's the there's the entry
point and if that's kept sort of under a
watchful eye rightly not like making it
into sort of meditation object just keep
it as a context that's it you can go
throughout your day without having to
worry about particular things and if you
lapse you can reestablish the context
because it's always there that's the
point the universals of renunciation freedom
the universals of renunciation freedom
from suffering it's on the basis of any
present experience and is always present
experience for as long as your life
these things I'm saying now it doesn't
make sense to somebody you can make that
into thing also so I have this pressure
to understand what I just listened to
why oh because they're going to be free
from suffering ah so what I just
listened to was talking about freedom
from suffering and I want to be free
from suffering so why don't I try and
understand it where my suffering is
right now not where my mind takes me in
terms of all this is mental
no so I won't understand this because I
want to be free from suffering right
here and now so where is this suffering
right here right now that needs to be
understood and then we go back to what
we spoke before how am I feeling right
now then so you're questioning your
contemplation you don't want to do it in
that like a like like a third person
sense when you're just thinking about it
based on designations or designations or
designation failing to see what each of
those nation actually designates in the
nation actually designates in the
present moment that's how you develop
concrete thinking not abstracting that's
why when you speak with is for people
have no concept of thinking completely
they would just think this is just all
theory and you make things concrete by
having a giant experience well what they
think John is but Jonna is the right
thinking thinking and pondering
that's impenetrable to desire and lust
that this amount to the entire central
domain as they will describe it that's
the John unshakeable thinking concrete
thinking results in janitors vijana is
not absolute and most people thinking is
abstract for them as in its divorced
from the present concrete concrete
situation so you wanna reduce earn it on
the right terms and see it and think
concretely that's what I mean don't jump into the
that's what I mean don't jump into the
answer that's going to be on the level
of abstract but discern it on the level
of presently reason situation that's
concrete that's that's fact I am I am I
am okay overall so you are clearly
thinking it all these are designations
but they pertain to the present enduring
phenomenon but if you go oh yes I am
okay but and it was women am i okay
means you thinking you're okay and
building everything else on top of it
took you away from presently because you
started doubting it because you can't
doubt the concrete phenomena oh is this
like this is is this what's my present
experience the whole or is a pleasant
experience of doubt and that's beyond
doubt so when concrete thinking becomes you
so when concrete thinking becomes you
know you pretty much can surmount any
hindrance that comes your way because
whatever hindrance is it it's a
hindrance in regard to like that with
pressures your worth or takes you
towards what confuses you apart but it
cannot be a hindrance in regard to its
own presence that's why the mindfulness
practice rightly he knows his mind is
mind affected by lost or mind free from
loss yeah last is present but it's not
like by thinking it concretely
you not affected by the loss losing the
sight of that concrete that's why there
is a
agree of like a temporary liberation
even though people were utterly
confusing their views and just keep
saying just be present be here now it
brings you back into that concreteness
and that's why it does have a release
nobody denies that but you want to
understand it
not just like go back now go back now be
present now because there is no
understanding which means none of the
habits that take you away from that
concrete moment are being understood
having not being understood you're not
free from those which means you're just
sort of resetting the problem so yeah
come back to present moment only to
realize that you can't be outside of a
present moment even if you want to only
to realize that the utmost of your
abstract thinking is concrete in itself
as a present layer is an experience and
then all the things that you thought
were abstract before or pure magic you
realize well they were only magic
because I was the one divorcing them
from reality but they in themselves
they're real as such then you can have
my main bodies and flying glide the suns
and whatever else you want to do because
it's not abstract anymore
so abstraction it's more an attitude
rather than the content of your thought
now there's someone who does understand
what you're talking about but he hears
your words your designations but he
doesn't see what they designate in his
experience yeah that's that's
abstraction for them but not because of
what you said but because of they don't
have the basis to discern this they
haven't discerned the basis for these
things so let's say how am I feeling
right now by giving a habitual answer
takes you usually in the level of that
abstraction but by looking how you're
feeling right now and then answering it
well that's concrete thinking now the
thought has a reason on a kind of a
concrete basis of a present enduring
feeling and that's where you want to
stay that's that context I talked about
and the context will cease to be the
context when he has drifted into
abstraction and lost any anchoring to
the basis of concrete situation and
mindfulness anchoring referencing
whatever that's the whole point
the principle of it is with my own
furnaces